Guide to the W. Duke, Sons & Co. Advertising Materials, 1880-1910
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
W. Duke, Sons & Co. Advertising Materials 1880-1910
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
W. Duke, Sons & Co.
5.0 linear feet Extent: 4000 Items
W. Duke, Sons & Co. was a tobacco manufacturer founded by Washington Duke in 1881. His son, James B. Duke, later became president of the American Tobacco Company. Collection includes tobacco trading cards, albums, and other advertising collectibles from the W. Duke Sons & Co., Liggett & Myers, American Tobacco, and other tobacco companies.
RL.00327
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The W. Duke, Sons & Co. Advertising Materials were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift. Formerly named the W. Duke, Sons & Co. Records.
Historical Note
W. Duke, Sons & Co. was a tobacco manufacturer founded by Washington Duke in 1881. His son, James B. Duke, later became president of the American Tobacco Company. For more information on Duke family history, please visit the University Archives.
Collection Overview
The W. Duke, Sons & Co. Advertising Collection includes a wide assortment of tobacco trading cards and other collectibles from the W. Duke, Sons & Co, Allen & Ginter, Kinney Bros. Co., Liggett & Myers, and many other tobacco brands. The collection has been arranged into Trading Cards, Booklets, Albums, and Assorted, depending on the format of the materials. The Trading Cards Series is by far the largest, and includes card collections of notable actresses, baseball players, public figures, and politicians, alongs with collections of country costumes, flags, wildlife, ships, musical instruments, and flowers. The Booklets series is a sort of subset of the trading cards, featuring small card-size booklets with stories and illustrations of famous people. The Albums Series includes bound scrapbooks, with individual collected cards, as well as albums published by the different tobacco companies that printed an entire series of cards. Finally, the Assorted Series includes stationary, oddly-shaped cards, background material, and cigarette boxes and tobacco pouches, some still full of cigarettes and tobacco.
Subject Headings
W. Duke, Sons & Co.; Allen & Ginter (Richmond, Va.); Goodwin and Co. (New York, N.Y.); Kinney Brothers (New York, N.Y.); Lone Jack Cigarettes Co. (Lynchburg, Va.); Marburg Bros. (Baltimore, Md.); S.F. Hesse and Co; Tobacco industry -- United States; Advertising -- Cigarettes; Advertising -- Tobacco; William S. Kimball & Co. (Rochester, N.Y.)
Contents of Collection
- Trading Cards, 1880-1910, (2 boxes)
  This series contains trading cards of various sizes and themes such as "Girls," "Actresses," "Coins of all Nations," and "Baseball Champions." The majority of these cards were distributed by W. Duke, Sons & Co., however other companies, such as Liggett & Myers, Allen & Ginter, American Tobacco, and Turkish Red, among others, are also represented.
  - W. Duke, Sons & Co. (Box 1)
    - Actresses, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Actresses (Cameo) (Box 1)
    - Portraits of Leading Actors and Actresses (Box 1)
    - Portraits of Leading Actors and Actresses (Long Cut) (Box 1)
    - Albums of American Stars, Battle Scenes,Bicycles and Trick Riders, and Bridges (Box 1)
    - Coins of All Nations and Fancy Dress Ball Costumes (Box 1)
    - Fishers & Fish and Flags (Box 1)
    - Girls (Box 2)
    - Governors of 48 States, Great Americans (Box 2)
    - Holidays, Musical Instruments (Box 2)
    - Ocean & River Steamers, Presidential Possibilities, and Puzzles (Box 2)
    - Postage Stamps (Box 2)
    - Sea Captains, Shadows, A Short History of..., Snapshots (Box 2)
    - Stars of the Stage, Terrors of America (Box 2)
    - Yacht Colors (Box 2)
    - 50 Scenes of Perilous Occupations, 50 Vehicles of the World (Box 2)
  - Allen & Ginter (Box 2)
    - Birds, Champions, Indian Chiefs, Parasols, Animals, Dudes, Smokers (Box 2)
    - Girls (Box 2)
  - American Tobacco (Box 2)
    - Battles, Floral Beauties, and Jokes (Box 2)
  - Cameron & Cameron (Box 2)
    - Girls (Box 2)
  - Goodwin & Co. (Box 3)
    - Girls (Box 3)
  - Hassan-Mecca Cigarettes (Box 3)
    - Champion Athletes (Box 3)
  - Kinney Bros. Co. (Box 3)
    - Girls, Sets 1-3 (Box 3)
    - Girls, Sets 4-5 (Box 3)
    - Baseball, Famous Ships (Box 3)
    - Famous Gems, Vessels of the World, and Leaders (Box 3)
    - Racehorses, Novelties, and Surf Beauties (Box 3)
    - Girls, Sets 1-3 (Box 3)
  - Liggett & Myers (Piedmont) (Box 3)
    - Baseball Players, Fish, and Landmarks (Box 3)
  - Lone Jack Cigarette Co. (Box 3)
    - Girls (Box 3)
  - Lorilland's Co. (Box 3)
    - Women (Box 3)
  - Marburg Cirgarettes (Box 3)
    - Actresses (Box 3)
  - Murad Cigarettes (Box 3)
    - College Series (Box 3)
  - S.F. & Hess Co. (Box 3)
    - Girls (Box 3)
  - Tareyton Cigarettes (Box 3)
    - Henry Series (Box 3)
  - Tobacco Products (Box 3)
    - Actors and Actresses (Box 3)
  - Turkey Red Cigarettes (Box 3)
    - Automobiles, Ships (Box 3)
  - Various Companies (Box 3)
    - Baseball and Actresses (Box 3)
    - Roses, Ships, and Assorted (Box 3)
  - W.S. Kimball & Co. (Box 3)
    - Goddesses of the Greeks and Romans (Box 3)
    - Ballet Queens, Butterflies, Fancy Bathers, Savage & Semi-Barbarous Chiefs and Rulers, Champions of Games & Sports (Box 3)
  - Unidentified Companies (Box 3)
    - Girls (Box 3)
    - Actresses (Box 3)
  - Cigarette Card Scrapbook (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook (oversize) of trading cards (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook of trading cards(adhered to the pages of a unidentified account book), circa late 19th/early 20th century (Box 9)
- Booklets, 1880-1910, (1 box)
  This series contains small booklets from cigarette packages. The booklets include an image on the cover and printed text inside.
  - Histories of Generals (Box 4)
  - Histories of Poor Boys Who Have Become Rich, and Other Famous People (Box 4)
- Assorted materials, 1880-1910, (1 box)
  This series includes a variety of other advertising materials, such as stationary, albums, and a set of watercolor prints produced by R. H. Macy & Co. which were distributed by various cigarette companies including W. Duke, Sons, & Co., among others. The series also includes information on the exhibition of these advertising materials at Duke University and the Duke Homestead Museum.
  - Stationary (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Letter from Elaine Stahl with Photocopies (Box 4)
  - Broadsides: Durham Warehouse Reams & Walker, Durham Business Directory (Box 4)
  - Exhibit Materials (Box 4)
  - Watercolors by Manning Studio, R.H. Macy & Co. (Box 4)
  - Fabric Inserts (Box 4)
  - Shape Cards: Buildings (Box 4)
  - Shape Cards: Boats (Box 4)
  - Tobacco Tax Fragment (Box 4)
  - Background Information (Box 4)
- Albums, 1880-1910, (1 box)
  This series contains albums produced by cigarette companies such as W. Duke, Sons & Co., Consols Cigarettes, and Allen & Ginter Co. These bound albums were produced for collectors of trading cards and reproduce the full series of cards such as "Costumes of All Nations" and "Yacht Colors of the World."
  - W. Duke, Sons & Co. (Box 5)
    - Costumes of All Nations (Box 5)
    - Postage Stamps (Box 5)
    - Governors' Coats of Arms (Box 5)
    - The Heroes of the Civil War (Box 5)
  - Kinney Bros. Co. (Box 5)
    - Shadows (Box 5)
    - Yacht Colors of the World (Box 5)
    - Bound volume of various W. Duke & Sons trading card albums (gift of Anne Roney) (Box 10)
  - Allen & Ginter Co. (Box 5)
    - The Napoleon Album (Box 5)
    - Album of World Champions (Box 5)
    - 50 Decorations of the Principal Orders of Knighthood (Box 5)
  - Kinney Bros. Co. (Box 5)
    - National Dances (Box 5)
  - Consols Cigarettes (Box 5)
    - Portraits of Ladies of the White House (Box 5)
  - J. L. Larkin & Co. (Box 5)
    - Sweet Home Album (Box 5)
  - Cigarette cases and tobacco pouches (Box 6)
    From companies including W. Duke, Sons & Co., Allen & Ginter, British-American Tobacco Co., and the American Tobacco Co.
- Tobacco Tags and Pins, (1 box)
  - Pins: Flags of the World, 1894, 1896 (Box 6)
  - Tobacco Tags, circa 1880s-1890s
    - P. Lorillard Co.: Climax Grade (large and small), Bullion Grade, Mechanics Delight, Green Turtle (large and small), Tenderloin, Sailors Delight, Army & Navy, 3 Black Crows, Clown, Cognac Cocktails-Climax Grade, Rose Bright Leaf (Box 6)
    - W & D Tobacco Co.: Staple (Box 6)
    - P. J. Sorg & Co.: Spear Ahead (Box 6)
    - J. B. Pace Tobacco Co.: White Cross (Box 6)
    - Wilson & McCallay Tobacco Co.: Gold Club (Box 6)
    - Wilson & McCallay Tobacco Co.: Gold Rope (Box 6)
    - Unidentified tobacco co.: Stars, No Tax, McNamara's Glory, Sultan, Variety, Silver Seal, Horseshoes, Roosters, Turtles, Honey-Dew, Hancock's Old Port, Hiawatha, Magnolia, Punch, Native Sons, McAlpin's Gold Shield, R.R. Plug, J.T., Rock and Rye, Extra-Quality Tobacco, Unidentified (cropping tool?) (Box 6)